<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A few vvords concerning conscience what it is; and what estate it was in before transgression. And how it became darkened, defiled and corrupted; and how again it may be enlightened, cleansed, purified and set at liberty, as it was before sin entred. Intermixt with a few words concerning persecution among the diverse sects in Christendom (and upon the face of all the earth); shewing, that they all arise for want of true liberty of conscience; and what that liberty is. William Shewen.</title>
            <author>Shewen, William, 1631?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221163</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832523</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832523</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2059:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A few vvords concerning conscience what it is; and what estate it was in before transgression. And how it became darkened, defiled and corrupted; and how again it may be enlightened, cleansed, purified and set at liberty, as it was before sin entred. Intermixt with a few words concerning persecution among the diverse sects in Christendom (and upon the face of all the earth); shewing, that they all arise for want of true liberty of conscience; and what that liberty is. William Shewen.</title>
                  <author>Shewen, William, 1631?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Few VVords Concerning CONSCIENCE, WHAT IT IS; And what Eſtate it was in before TRANSGRESSION. And how it became Darkened, Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and Corrupted; And how again it may be Enlightened, Cleanſed, Purified and ſet at Liberty, as it was before Sin entred.</p>
            <p>Intermixt with a few Words concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Perſecution</hi> among the diverſe Sects in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> (and upon the Face of all the Earth); ſhewing, that they all ariſe for Want of True Liberty of Conſcience; and what that <hi>Liberty</hi> is.</p>
            <p>William Shewen.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:36997:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36997:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:36997:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36997:3"/>
            <head>A Few VVords Concerning CONSCIENCE, What it is, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>COnſcience</hi> is generally to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be ſuch a Being, Subject,
<note place="margin">Which Capacity is as a Book, capable to contain what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or imprinted ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and may be not only opened and ſhut, but blotted and ſtained alſo.</note> Faculty or Capacity in Mankind, which is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the Beaſts of the Field, Fiſh of the Sea, and Fowls of the Air; and in this Capacity Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind differs from and excels them all; being created in and endued with ſuch a Capacity, wherein and whereby he is enabled to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of the Divine Nature, &amp; to partake of the Beams of its Glory, to Meditate Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, Conſolate, Delight and Refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36997:4"/>in the Light, Law and Glory of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; which Capacity is not to be found in all the Elements of this World, but only in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>Now, in the Beginning Man's <hi>Mind, Heart</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> was a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and pure Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle,
<note place="margin">Theſe Three are ſo inſeparable, that that which defiles the One, defiles the Other; and that which purifies the One, purifies the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Tabernacle and Dwelling place for the Almighty; his Power, Wiſdom, Light and Glory was diſplayed therein, and Mankind was highly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereby, above all the Works of his hands. And while Mankind ſtood here in this High and Heavenly E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
<note place="margin">The Bleſſed Eſtate of Man before the Fall.</note> he lived in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice of God, enjoying the Light of his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and had Unity with his Maker, and could behold his Face with Joy, and receive the Reflections of the Beams of Divine Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhining in his Conſcience with Delight, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Dominion over all the Creation; his Conſcience being Pure, he held the Myſtery of Faith in it, eying the Inviſible God through, above and beyond all things, viſible and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36997:4"/>
            <p> This was the State of Mankind before the Fall, while his Conſcience was Pure and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled; while he remain'd in that Eſtate God made him and placed him in, who was a Pure, Innocent Subject, Holy in his Being, and Harmleſs in his Nature, all within him and without him was Good, yea, very Good. Now, the Wiſdom is to underſtand, how that which was Holy and Harmleſs, Innocent, Pure and Undefiled, did become Evil and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſeeing in this State and Time Evil had not a Being, whence could or did the Temptations ariſe? The Wiſdom of all men living in the Faln Defiled Eſtate cannot find out nor ſearch into the Depth of theſe things;
<note place="margin">The Myſteries of God are hid from the Wiſe and Prudent, and revealed to Babes.</note> they are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly revealed and made known by the ſhining of the ſame Light which was in the Beginning, and gives the Children there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ſee to the ſame: Therefore to the ſame Light and Spirit of God, which moved upon the Face of the Waters, in the Beginning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun, Moon and Stars were created, or the Mountains formed; which Light now ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the Heart of Mankind (though Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs), which Light alſo God hath cauſed to ſhine out of Darkneſs in the Hearts of Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36997:5"/>in this our Day and Age; I ſay, To this Light I chiefly refer and commend thee, being indeed the Key of the Myſteries of God and Godlineſs, yet a few Words for the ſake of the Captivated, and for the opening of that Eye that's blinded, that ſuch may come to ſee and diſcern the Things of God, and that the Enlightned may by ſeeing perceive how Mankind at firſt came to make Shipwrack of Faith and a Good Conſcience, and avoid doing the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the Author of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with an Excellent Spirit of Wiſdom and Diſcerning, when he comprized the Hiſtory of the Creation, and the State of Mankind therein; and indeed I muſt tell my <hi>Reader,</hi> That nothing ſhort of a Meaſure of the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Divine Wiſdom can lead thee into a True Diſcerning &amp; Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſame;
<note place="margin">Nothing ſkort of the Inſpiration of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty gives a True Underſtanding of the things of his Kingdom.</note> he hath expoſed the Shell, but hath lockt up the Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel from the Prudent Wit and Comprehenſion of Man under divers <hi>Similitudes</hi> and <hi>Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicks;</hi> thou mayeſt read the Hiſtory, and walk in the Field of the Creation, yet if thou diggeſt not deep, and find the Pearl, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it, and like a Wiſe Merchant Man ſell All for it, thou wilt be ignorant of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36997:5"/>and remain Poor, Blind and Miſerable; for I intend not to throw Pearls before Swine, neither dare I (like <hi>Hezekiah</hi>) ſhew the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Lord's Houſe to the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> leſt both I and it are carried into Captivity therefore.</p>
            <p>Now, its ſaid, <hi>They were both
<note n="*" place="margin">Many Carnal Conceits and Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations are and have been at Work among Men to Underſtand theſe things, but they have not come to the Opening of the Seals, nor to the Key of the Myſteries of God, and ſo have divulged their own Carnal and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifrian Conceptions, Comprehenſions, and Notions for the Divine Knowledge of God; and many have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by grown Rich, Tall and Great in Brain and Head-Knowledge; but Poor, Low and Small in Experimental Heart Underſtanding, and of the Work of God therein.</note> Naked, the Man and his Wife, and were not aſhamed:</hi> There was then No Cauſe of Shame in being, no Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation entred into, no Sin committed, which is the Cauſe of Shame. And its alſo ſaid, <hi>The Serpent was more ſubtil then all the Beaſts of the Field which God had made:</hi> Now God made nothing but what was Good, keeping in its State &amp; Bounds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God had ſet and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, would ſo have remained; But there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a poſſibility to break thoſe Bounds, and diſobey that Law that God had ſet over them, God gave Mankind A Warning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36997:6"/>thereof, and acquainted him with the Penalty thereof alſo, that <hi>in the Day he did it, he ſhould Dye the Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Mankind had Faith in his Maker, and in his Conſcience found himſelf bound to obey the Command given him, and had Strength to reſiſt the Temptation,
<note place="margin">Theſe Things are to be ſeen and known in the Light, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, beyond what Words can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</note> till the Woman (the weaker Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel) believed a Lye, and looked upon the Beauty of the Thing preſented, and let up a Deſire to be wiſe, and to know good and evil, and to be as Gods; ſo in this Hope of gaining and bettering their Eſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſubject unto * Vanity, and hereby the Light that ſhined in the Heart and Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came vailed,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.20.</note> and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Glory of God that appeared therein,
<note place="margin">Every particular within themſelves muſt come to know the Loſs and full Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion, and Death of the one, and the Life and Reſurrection of the other, before Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration can be known.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came loſt as the Image of the Selfiſh Will and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire roſe up, and became prevalent, the Image of God declined, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and when man loſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36997:6"/>his Faith, which was held in the pure Conſcience,
<note n="†" place="margin">The ſame befals Mankind at this Day when they looſe their Anchor.</note> which Faith was as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, by which Conſcience as a Ship in a Storm was ſtaied for a while, from being made a wrack; I ſay when he loſt this Faith in the Word and Command of God, and believed the Serpent's Lyes, he ſoon made Shipwrack of both: and no ſooner were their own Eyes opened, but the Eye and Light of God, which ſhined in them became ſtopped, and vailed, and they loſt the Glory and Benefit of it; no ſooner their own Wiſdom and Knowledge ſprung up; but the Wiſdom of God departed, and Innocency the heavenly Clothing became loſt, and Nakedneſs appeared, Faith and a good Conſcience deſtroyed, Shame, Guilt, Fear and Hiding the Effects of it ſucceeded: So though Conſcience in its primitive Eſtate was Pure, Clean and Undefiled,
<note n="*" place="margin">The ſame Danger is ſtill, even among ſuch as are preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a Chaſt Virgin to Chriſt, and have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to an innocent Sinleſs Eſtate, and a Dwelling-Place in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; therefore the Duty of all ſuch is to watch and pray, that they enter not into Temptation, and are beguiled as the <hi>Serpent</hi> did <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </note> yet was liable and capable to be corrrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, darkened and defiled, even as the Mind depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from a due Regard and obedience of the Law and Command of God, and ſleighted his Light and Glory, which ſhined, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36997:7"/>illuminated his Heart and Conſcience; then Clouds of Error, and Miſts, and Fogs of Self-will thoughts and Imaginations ſoon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, and darkened the pure Air, and ecclipſed the Glory of that Sun, that before ſhined in him, &amp; drew a vail before the Light of God's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10.</note> which to behold was his Joy, and Delight; now become his Fear &amp; Terror, now a Night come over him, &amp; he runs in the Darkneſs thereof to hide himſelf among the Trees of the Garden from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God; this was the Way and Work of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in the Beginning, and his Children are found in the ſame at this Day up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Face of the whole Earth, he that readeth let him underſtand.</p>
            <p>Now when this noble Part or Capacity in Man is thus clouded, and darkened, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed through Diſobedience to the Law of his God, he then goeth aſtray more and more, corrupteth himſelf through his Imaginations and Inventions more and more, and according to that he entertaineth and joins himſelf to; ſo becomes even Darkneſs and a Child of it:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17.</note> And of the moſt excellent, and beſt Part of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36997:7"/>becomes the worſt, and the principalleſt Inſtrument in the Hand of the wicked One to lead, even Nature it Self, out of its Courſe, and to burden, oppreſs, corrupt and abuſe all Things under his Power, verifying that Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im among Men, <hi>The beſt of things being corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted become the worſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this Degenerate, Faln, Clouded, Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and Corrupted Eſtate the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and holy Principle of Light, which at firſt ſhined clear in the Conſcience
<note n="*" place="margin">Though Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind fell from and loſt the Light and Glory of God, yet that in it ſelf remain'd the ſame, and became his Judge and Reprover, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was his Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> remains in it ſelf the ſame, pure and undefiled, and doth glance forth its Eternal Beams of Light into this Darkneſs, and gives Mankind in that Eſtate ſome Senſe and Knowledge of their Loſt, Degenerated, Corrupted, Miſerable Eſtate; and in the Cool of the Day calls Tranſgreſſing Man to an Account, as it did <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> and convinceth them of their Evil Deeds, and calls to a Repentance or Returning again into the ſame Way he went out of, even by the Help and Guidance of that Light and Holy Spirit which at firſt ſhined in his Heart and Conſcience, wherein he enjoyed the Light of God's Countenance, and walked and lived in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36997:8"/>his Preſence without Rebuke. But being Departed, Degenerated and Turned in his Mind from the Good into the Evil, from the Glory and Light that once ſhined in him, and and was pleaſant for his Eye to behold, into Sin and Tranſgreſſion; he is by it purſued, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and convinced, in order to turn him back again: And whoſoever hearkens to this Reproof, and obeyes the Spirit of Truth,
<note n="‖" place="margin">The Way to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe and a Undefiled Eſtate again.</note> which convinceth of Sin, and loves the Hand that ſmites them, and ſubmitteth to the ſame, ſhall come to witneſs and enjoy the Undefiled, Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Happy Eſtate again, and enter in through the Gate into the City and Paradife of God again. But he that hates the Reproofs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and rebells againſt the Spirit, and humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not himſelf under the Mighty Hand of God, which ſmites for Tranſgreſſion, goes forward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to utter Darkneſs, ſtumbles &amp; falls, and riſes no more to the Reſurrection of Life and Felicity, but is filled with Fear, and encompaſſed with Terrors round about, upwards and downwards, nothing but Tribulation, Anguiſh and Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit attends Mankind in this Eſtate, wherein his chief Companions are a Guilty Defiled Conſcience,
<note place="margin">☞</note> wherein are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Grievous Things againſt him, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36997:8"/>a Wounded Spirit, a Burden too heavy for <hi>Cain</hi> to bear; though but the Fruit of his own Doings, and the Crop of his own ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
            <p>Now, in this State of Loſs, Miſery and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, wherein the Heart and Conſcience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed and Corrupted, there is great Working and Contriving in the minds of Mankind how to find that again which is loſt, and how to be delivered from the Miſery and Bondage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is faln; and this is the Nature of all Mankind in the Fall to ſeek out many Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to go down to <hi>Egypt</hi> for Help, and to walk by the Light of his own Fire, and the Sparks that he hath kindled, and in the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Wayes of his own finding out, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Help, Counſel and ſtraight Way of the Lord; he being darkened and deceived, and the Light of Chriſt in his Conſcience vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he ever did and doth at this day, in that Eſtate, take one thing for another, viz.
<note place="margin">Degenerate man in all Ages ever was Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and alwayes took one thing for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; Good for Evil, and Evil for Good; Light for Darkneſs, &amp; Darkneſs for Light, &amp;c. which Miſtake is the Ground of all Error and Miſchief in the World in matters of Religion.</note> Good for Evil, and Evil for Good, Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light, &amp;c. And being thus far decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36997:9"/>exalts and ſets up the one for the other, ſo when he hath found out a Way and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that liketh him, and ſewed ſomething to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, though but leaves, he will endeavour to cover his Nakedneſs therewith, and to hide himſelf from the Wrath that is revealed in him, and awakened againſt him, and when he hath invented a Medicine to cure his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a Salve to heal his Wound, though deceitfully, and found Mortar to daub up the Breach, though it be untempered, his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being darkened, and his Heart deceived, he will plead Conſcience for the Uſe of the ſame and ſets them up as the only Remedies to be found, &amp;c. So natural is it for degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Man to worſhip the Works of his own hands, and to follow the Inventions, Conceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Thoughts &amp; Imaginations of his own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Heart, &amp; yet calls it the Way of the Lord, and if any of his Neighbours, or Brethren come to hear and obey the Voice of God, and to follow the Light, and Guidance of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; to find Acceptance with him, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in a good Conſcience to God to follow his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<note place="margin">The Cauſe of <hi>Cain</hi>'s Anger againſt his Brother, or the Wicked againſt the Righteous in this Age.</note> and to make Uſe of his invented Means, and to bow down and worſhip the Image he hath ſet up,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36997:9"/>then Envy and Hatred ariſeth, and Violence breaks forth, and Blood toucheth Blood, even becauſe ſuch will not, nor cannot for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, ſee, &amp; ſay, and do as he doth; bow to his Image and Invention, and worſhip as he doth, though he finds not Acceptance of God, nor the Light of his Countenance towards him in his Worſhip, no more then <hi>Cain</hi> that Religious Murderer did, whoſe Offering was the Fruit of that Ground that's curſed, which never did, nor never will bring forth Fruit well-pleaſing to God: And it is from Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind labouring in this Ground (being driven out of the Paradiſe and Garden of God) that all the Diverſity of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Notions,
<note place="margin">The Riſe of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Cauſe of Cruelty, and Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about them.</note> Concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, Thoughts, Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Contrvances, Forms and Faſhions of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Worſhip upon the Face of the whole Earth ſpringeth and ariſeth, and all the Envy, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Cruelty, Bloodſhed, Compelling Force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Perſecution, about Faſhions of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Religion among all the Sects in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ariſeth from this Ground, and all that are found in the Work thereof (though they may pretend Conſcience, and Zeal to God, and the Maintenance of the Goſpel, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36997:10"/>the Good of Souls) are of the Spirit of <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt Murderer about Religion, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they will find meaſured into their own Boſoms from the Hand of God.</p>
            <p>Now the divers Sects, and formal Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> are ready to ſtand up plead, and contend for their Forms and Invention, and Way and Manner of Worſhip, &amp; alſo cry out for Liberty of Conſcience in their Way, and for the Practice of their Faſhion in Worſhip, and will alſo in their Infancy cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Perſecution;
<note place="margin">Every Selfiſh private narrow Spirit Sect and Opinion, though in its Riſe may pretend otherwiſe hath Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution at the Bottom.</note> when they want only Number; Power &amp; Strength to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute themſelves, which when they attain unto, and their Horns grow ſtrong, and get Crowns upon them, they will, and have been found doing the ſame Work, as might be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated at large; but being obvious to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Judicious, and intending Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, I forbear; and indeed they can do no otherwiſe, being of a private, narrow, ſelf-conceited Spirit, ignorant of the true Liberty of Conſcience, which Liberty ſtands not in this or that, or the other invented Form or Faſhion of Worſhip, Conceiving or Opinion; but in the Light &amp; Power of God, which every particular
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36997:10"/>Man and Woman upon the Face of all the whole Earth ought to know, and experience enlightening and ruling in his Conſcience, and Conſcience can never enjoy its true Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty till it come into this Eſtate.
<note place="margin">☞</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſciences of Men are generally weak, darkened defiled, corrupted, vitiated, (and which is worſt of all, ſome who have loſt the Day of their Viſitation, are ſeared as with an hot Iron) and in this State have a Bond and Tye upon their Conſciences, which ought to be broken, and caſt off, till which, they are liable to make Conſcience of ſuch Things they ought not; as might be inſtanced through all Sects, both among <hi>Indians, Turks, Jews</hi> and <hi>Titular Chriſtians,</hi> and the Evils and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that enſue from hence are very many.</p>
            <p>Conſcience in the State above,
<note place="margin">☞</note> is the great Troubler of the World of Mankind, and the Evils that are brought forth and committed, under the Notion, Pretence and Seal of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, are Evils of the greateſt Magnitude.</p>
            <p>Now nothing under Heaven is able to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Conſcience, enlighten, cleanſe, and purifie, and redeem it into true Liberty; but the Light and Power of God, ſhining and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating in the Conſcience, as it did before Tranſgreſſion entered,
<note place="margin">What alone is able to bring Liberty of Conſcience.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sin was committed, and before Opinion, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36997:11"/>dark Thoughts and Imaginations ſprung up; this alone is able to purge and cleanſe the Conſcience, from Darkneſs and dead Works, and make it an undefiled Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for God again, as it was in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; this is the State wherein Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is known and enjoyed, even when Man comes to have his Conſcience ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in,
<note place="margin">☞</note> and ruled and governed by the Light, Spirit and Power of God, then man's Heart becomes his Throne, and he ſits and rules therein, and that which uſurped it, is caſt down and the Prince of the Air, which got his rule and place there by Diſobedience, is caſt out.</p>
            <p>And all thoſe that come not to know this brought to paſs within themſelves,
<note place="margin">☞</note> nor are not in the Way, that leadeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are but of a private ſelfiſh Opinion and Sect; though (as above) while they are little and low, and ſmall in Number, they may plead for Liberty of Conſcience, and cry againſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, Force, Impoſition and Violence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion; yet when their Opinion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, and the Horns thereof grow ſtrong thereby they will puſh towards the Eaſt, Weſt, North and South, and will ſmite their fellow-Servants; and as I have ſaid before, it can be no otherwiſe then ſo, until man comes to know the univerſal Light and Spirit of God to ſhine
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36997:11"/>&amp; rule in his Conſcience,
<note place="margin">☞</note> &amp; eſtabliſh it in perfect Liberty, and Love to the whole Creation of God, and to all the Works of his Hands, and in Obedience to all his holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; in this ſtands the perfect Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Now for want of this the <hi>Titular Chriſtians</hi> of all Sorts and Sects, are ſo wedded to their private &amp; ſelfiſh Opinions, Traditions, Notions, Conceptions, Apprehenſions, Comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Thoughts and Imaginations about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Church and Worſhip, and matters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Conſcience, that they envy, hate, bite and devour one another about them. One will perſecute about his <hi>Maſs Book</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Altar</hi> another about his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer-Book, Maintenance</hi> and <hi>Church-Diſcipline,</hi> another about his <hi>Directory:</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other about his <hi>Church-Faith</hi> and <hi>Agreement of the Aſſembly of Divines</hi> (ſo called) and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> and <hi>Water, Dayes</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> and other <hi>outward Things:</hi> They will quarrel with tear and devour one another, and all like ſo many ravenous Beaſts will prey upon the Sheep,
<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim;</hi> but both againſt <hi>Judith:</hi> Every Sect in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendim,</hi> one againſt another, devided like the Builderrs of <hi>Babel;</hi> yet all againſt the tender, meek, harmleſs, Lamb like Spirit of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36997:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>whomſoever it appears, that in all Ages ſince the Fall and Apoſtacy grew up as a Lilly among Thornes, prik'd on every Side,
<note place="margin">A Thorn may hurt a Lilly, but a Lilly cannot hurt a Thorn.</note> &amp; as a Lamb among wolves, which though hurt and prey'd upon, wants the very Nature &amp; Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of hurting again, or rendring Evil for Evil, even as an outward Lilly doth a Thorn, or a Lamb a Wolf.</p>
            <p>So that this is an infallible Sign and Token, both of the one and the other,
<note place="margin">☞</note> of him whoſe Conſcience is at Liberty to ſerve the Lord, and loves his whole Creation, and is at Unity and Peace therewith: and of him who hath his Conſcience bound under a private Opinion, corrupted and defiled with Envy, Hatred and Evil-Will againſt his Brother, and Neighbour, about Matters of Sacrifice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Faith and Worſhip And whoever thou art, and of what Opinion ſoever thou art, hereby thou mayſt meaſure and try thy ſelf, and find of what Generation and Stock thou art of, whether of the righteous, or the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; whether thou art a Lilly or a Thorn, a Lamb or a Wolf; and whether thy Conſcience be at Liberty or bound: If thou find a Mind, Will or Inclination in thee,
<note place="margin">An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Signe where Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Liberty.</note> to <hi>Envy, Hate, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36997:12"/> &amp; lay violent Hands like</hi> Cain, upon thy Brother and Neighbour, thou mayſt aſſure thy ſelf, and infallibly know, that thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is degenerated &amp; defiled, and that thou art born of the Fleſh, and that thou art a Thorn, and no Lilly, a Wolf and no Lamb: And this Fleſh thou art born of, is the Fleſh of the Whore the falſe Church, which hath drunk the Blood of the Saints, and Martyrs in all Ages; and this Whore thy Mother, hath not only nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee up; but made thee drunk with the Wine of her Fornication; and thou art a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of <hi>Myſtery Babylon</hi> the great, and a Stranger to the beloved City of God, and a hater of thoſe, that dwell therein; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thou mayſt have a golden cup of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which thy Mother holds forth to the Nations; yet thy Conſcience is defiled and thy Heart corrupted, and ſo far darkened and captivated under Bondage &amp; ſtrong Deluſion, that notwithſtanding thou appeareſt like a Thorn,
<note place="margin">A perfect Sign of one that is made drunk with the Wine of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</note> and in the Nature of a Wolf, hurting the Lilly, and worrying the Lamb; yet thou thinks, thou art doing God good Service therein, being made ſo drunk with the Whore's Cup, and blinded in thy ſuperſtitious Zeal, that thou takes the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36997:13"/>Lilly for a Thorn, and the Lamb for a Wolf, and the Whore, thy Mother, for the Lamb's Wife.</p>
            <p>And now this is an infallible Sign where Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience is enjoyed, where the Light, Love and Power of God rules in the Conſcience; ſuch if his Brother or Neighbour hath his Conſcience in Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,
<note place="margin">A true infallible Sign where Liberty of Conſcienc is enjoyed</note> or is weak, being vailed and darkned ſo far as to believe a Lye, and to make Conſcience of doing that, which he ought not to do, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to worſhip as the <hi>Maſs-Book</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, or as the <hi>Common Prayer-Book, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory, Church-Faith, Aſſembly of Divines</hi> (ſo called) or as any other invented Platform of Religion Commands, I ſay he that hath his Conſcience truely enlightened,
<note place="margin">☞</note> and is a Chriſtian indeed, doth not hate and envy his Brother or Neighbour therefore neither hath he any evil Will towards him in, this Eſtate, and hath no more inclination to put forth his Hand againſt his Perſon, Life, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty or Eſtate, becauſe of his Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Errors, and Religious Practices, then he hath againſt his own Life; but inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the univerſal Love of God, finds it his Duty to pitty ſuch in his Heart; and having obtained Liberty of Conſcience himſelf, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36997:13"/>found the univerſal Medicine, which if appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is able to cure all ſick and feeble Minds, wounded Spirits, weak and diſtempered Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, he is willing and ready to tell his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Neighbour, what the Lord hath done for his Soul, and how and where he came to find the precious Pearl, and to inform and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them how they may find the ſame, and exhort and perſwade them to receive and make uſe and tryal of the ſame Medicine that hath cured him, though for this his Love and good Will, he meets with much Exerciſe and Hardſhip from the ill-natured and Ignorant, and much Oppoſition and Scorn from the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh-wiſe and prudent; this was the Portion of the righteous, and Miniſters of the everlaſting Goſpel from the ungrateful World in all Ages, * who were conſtrained in the Love of God to run to and fro among them,
<note place="margin">The Work and End of the true Miniſtry.</note> that Knowledge might be enereaſed, and to warn Men to flee from the Wrath which is to come; and knowing the Terrors of the Lord, perſwaded Men to be reconciled to God: Thus they did and do in Obedience to him, and Love to their Souls (and not for Gold and Silver, and ſelfiſh Ends; but to diſcharge their Conſciences in the Sight of God) this hath been the Labour of Love,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36997:14"/>and Travail of the righteous in all Ages, who come to have their Conſciences made tender, and truly enlightened, cleanſed, purified and ſet at Lberty from all that did defile them; they never perſecuted hated, hurt or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any about Matters of Conſcience and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, though erronious in their Opinions, and ſuperſtitious in their Practices;
<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>neither ought any to be troubled, vexed and ruined in their Perſons, Liberties, Lives and Eſtates becauſe of thoſe Things, especially when their Opinions tend not to the Ruin, Hurt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Mankind, and his outward well being and humane Society:</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> But ſome ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions there are, which indeed are as Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in Nature, deſtroying natural Affection, Violating the Bounds of Humanity, under the Cloak and Pretence of Religion and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; and ſome are ſo far beſotted in their Opinions, that they will plead Conſcience for the Proſecution of them, though thereby they lay waſte the Property, Life and Liberty of Perſons that are of a contrary, or different mind and Judgment to them, though better livers then themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now the End of all good Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among Men,
<note place="margin">The End of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; true Government.</note> is to preſerve and defend their Properties, Liberties and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36997:14"/>Lives from the Teeth, and Mouthes of ſuch as would ſpoil and rob them of either. And among all the Beaſts of prey this <hi>blind Zeal, miſguided Conſcience and dark ſelfiſh Opinion</hi> is moſt ravenous, this Wolf in Sheeps Cloathing hath ſharp Teeth and cruel Clawes, and a wilde, untamed, devouring Spirit, notwithſtanding his pretence of Zeal and Conſcience for the Chriſtian Religion; 'tis the Spirit of <hi>Cain</hi> &amp; <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Blind Zeal, a defiled Conſcience private ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiſh dark Opinions, the Ground of divers Maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſacries and much Blood ſhed in <hi>Christendom.</hi>
               </note> that Murderer and Perſecutor about Sacrifice and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which will be riſing up againſt his Brother and Neighbour; as it hath been, ſo it is at this Day, he that is born of the Fleſh will perſecute him that is born of the Spirit, &amp;c. But whoſoever is led by his (religious or rather) irreligious Opinions to endeavour the Hurt and Ruin of his Brother or Neighbour about matters of Religion and Conſcience; if he accompliſh and effect the fame, he is an <hi>Evil Doer,</hi> and ought to ſuffer as an <hi>Evil-Doer;</hi> and he that hoth Good-will to all, and ſeeks the good of all, and hurts no man though he be of a contrary Mind and Judgment to him, and of a defiled Conſcience, and erronious Opinions, he is the <hi>Well-Door.</hi> And the Laws of God and all good Men, who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36997:15"/>are appointed to Rule for God, are a <hi>Terror to the One, and a Praiſe and Encouragement to the Other:</hi> And ſuch brutiſh unnatural <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioniſts,</hi> whoſe Conſciences are not only dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, defiled and corrupted, but feared as with a hot Iron: who, under the Profeſſion of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> dare entertain and aſſert ſuch Cruel Impious Tenets or Opinions, as, that it is lawful to Deſtroy the Property, Liberty and Life of Men about the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion; &amp; to account all that conform not to his Form and Faſhion of Religion, Tradition and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention no better then Weeds and Vermine, Corrupt and Cankered Members, fit to be pulled up, cut off, burnt and deſtroyed, where this Ravenons Beaſt is prevalent, as in ſome Countries beyond the Seas, it deſtroyes every Green Thing, this <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Bloody Opinion</hi> is hated of God and all Good Men, and is as a Monſter riſen out of the Bottomleſs Pit, and as the great <hi>Apollyon,</hi> or Deſtroyer, to be chained and ſhut up therein again: <hi>Oh God! haſten the Time thereof is the Breathing of the Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! how Lamentable is it to conſider what Work and Havock this Spirit hath made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Corrupt, Blind, Miſ guided Conſcience, and Ignorant Zeal, eſpecially in this Part of the World, called <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> about <hi>Church,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36997:15"/>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> the <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> (the beſt and nobleſt Capacity of Man being in its primitive Eſtate) when darkned, defiled, corrupted, hardned and ſeared, becomes the worſt, even a Habitation for Devils, <hi>formed</hi> and <hi>transformed</hi> like unto an Angel of Light; ſo that thoſe that are not deceived and ruled by the One, may be the Other:
<note place="margin">The Greateſt and Strongeſt Poyſon of Souls, Bodies, Lives, &amp;c. of Men is in the Whore's Golden Cup; and all that drink free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereof (or are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thereto) are deeply infected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with And the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reel with the Wine of her Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> But in all Ages the * tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Devil, who aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Form of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Profeſſion of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, hath proved the greateſt Deceiver, and the moſt Cruel, as might be evidenced at large by his Work in this preſent Age, and throughout the Records of many Generations.</p>
            <p>But all that come to return in their Minds to the Light and Glory of God,
<note place="margin">The Way out of all Selfiſh and Private O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and Cruelty about them, into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Freedom and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience.</note> which at firſt ſhined in the Heart &amp; Conſcience of Mankind, &amp; made it a fit Receptacle or Dwelling-place for himſelf, &amp; belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, walks &amp; abides in the ſame, ſhall again come to <hi>know</hi> &amp; <hi>live</hi> in the ſame
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36997:16"/>Eſtate man enjoyed before his Conſcience was defiled, before the Vail came over his Heart and Underſtanding, before the Image of God was loſt, before any Place or Credit was given to the Serpent's Lyes; where true <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> was lived in, and the Light of God's Countenance enjoyed, the <hi>Serpent ruled over,</hi> and the <hi>Earth ſubdued,</hi> in the Paradiſe of God, The Light that now ſhineth out of Darkneſs in the Hearts of Thouſands and Ten Thouſands, leads not only into theſe things; but farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Life &amp; State of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> againſt whom the Serpent never could nor ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail: And the God of Heaven and Earth, who hath cauſed or commanded it to ſhine, hath the Praiſe and Glory thereof, both now and for evermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36997:16"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>SUch <hi>Opinions</hi> in Religion, which bind man's Conſcience to ſeek and endeavour the Hurt of his Brother or Neighbour, in his Name, Perſon, Liberty, Eſtate or Life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth not believe and practiſe the ſame Manner and Form of Worſhip as he doth, are very Cruel, Unnatural and Unreaſonable; <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe many times People come by their <hi>Opinions</hi> as Heirs come by their <hi>Eſtates</hi> Hereditarily; if their Parents or Tutors were of this or that Sect of the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> their Children commonly are trained up and educated in the ſame; if of one of the Sects among the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> (ſo called), then commonly the Child is trained and catechiſed in the ſame; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Parents take as much Care to leave their Children poſſeſſed of their <hi>Religious Opinions,</hi> as they do of their Eſtates, as might be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at large, both among <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> the greateſt Proof many have to prove themſelves <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> is, that their Parents and Tutors were
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36997:17"/>ſo called and accounted, and they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and walked in their Traditions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Orders and Diſcipline of Holy Church (ſo called), and they believe as the Church believes; and 'tis their Opinion, this is <hi>Chriſtianity enough to carry them to Heaven,</hi> many being bound in their Conſciences by a traditional implicite Faith to their Hereditary <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> or the Traditions of their Fore-Fathers, that they never Queſtion their Way nor Title therein; they never knew no other, nor better, nor dare not for Fear ſeek further, their Conſciences being bound under their private traditional Opinions and Ceremonies: Now, that ſuch ſhould have their Bodies hurt, and their Lives deſtroyed, and their Eſtates rent from them and their Poſterity, becauſe they will not change and renounce their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions they have been bred up and educated in, and conform to that Opinion and Form of Worſhip that hath the Sword in its Hand, and is become National in the Country where he lives, is both Cruel, Unnatural and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, whether he be <hi>Jew, Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, Chriſtian, Papiſt</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Becauſe no man is able to change his Own Mind in Religion when he pleaſeth, or when commanded, nor break thoſe Chains of Tradition he hath been educated in from his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36997:17"/>Childhood; neither is he able to ſhake off thoſe Bolts and Fetters of Opinion, and change his Faith and Belief, when he pleaſeth: For when man's Conſcience is defiled with Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Opinions, and his Mind and Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding darkened, and bound under the Chains thereof, he is not able to deliver himſelf, nor to purifie his own Conſcience, nor enlighten his own Underſtanding, nor can any man deliver the Soul of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: nothing leſs then the Knowledge and Experience of the Light, Spirit and Mighty Power of God's appearing and ſhining in the Conſcience, and enlightening the Mind and Underſtanding, breaking the Priſon-Doors of Opinion, and pulling down the Strong Hold of Imagination, is able to effect thoſe things; therefore all ſuch as have their Conſciences purified, their Minds and Underſtandings thereby enlightened, are delivered and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from the Spirit of Envy and Cruelty; and from all private Opinions and Bondage of Darkneſs, and lives and walks in the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, which brings Peace on Earth and Good-will to Men; and ſuch never Envyed any, nor Hurt any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, though <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! the Weight and Burden of this envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Bloody Spirit of <hi>Perſecution</hi> in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:36997:18"/>which is ſate down in the Throne of Conſcience, and wrapt about with the Mantle of Zeal for Religion, is very great and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous; it is the greateſt Burden the Earth bears, and the greateſt Troubler of the World of Mankind; 'tis the great Whore that <hi>John</hi> ſaw ride upon the Scarlet coloured Beaſt, and ſate upon the Waters; and it is the Beaſt he ſaw riſe out of the Earth, with two Horns like a Lamb, yet ſpeaks like a Dragon, and makes Fire come down from Heaven, in the Sight of Men, and cauſeth all both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free and bond to receive a Mark in their right Hand, or in their Fore-Heads, that no Man might buy or ſell, ſave he that had the Mark or the Name of the Beaſt, or the Number of his Name; this Spirit is the Womb, out of which ſpringeth all the Force and Violence, and cruel Inventions of Torture and ſpoil of Bodies, Goods and Liberties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Difference in Opinion, Faith and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which as is ſaid before, is cruel, unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and unnatural becauſe by the Laws of God &amp; all good Men,
<note place="margin">☞</note> no Man ought to ſuffer, but according to the Nature of his Offence; if his Offence be viſible, natural and corporal, &amp; belonging to things of this world, then his Puniſhment ought to be natural, and corporal, and viſibly executed upon him; if his Offence be ſpiritual, and relating to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36997:18"/>inviſible Things of the Mind, Heart and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in Matters of Faith and Worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, &amp; the Life &amp; World to come, then their Puniſhment is to be ſpiritual and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpiritually; and the Weapons to be uſed againſt ſuch, are not to be carnal: The Bodies of Men ought not to be inquiſition'd and tortur'd,
<note place="margin">What Perſecution is.</note> nor their Goods ſpoyled for the errors of their Minds, or the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their religious Perſwaſions; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this is ſound and practiſed, it may be juſtly called cruel and unreaſonable, and bloody Perſecution, though under the Pretence of Conſcience, and Zeal for Religion: And the true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and Church of Chriſt, never had, nor ever will have a Hand in ſuch Work; it is the Whore the falſe Church, and her Children,
<note place="margin">The Beaſt, the Whore, the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the three un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Spirits, Myſtery-Babylon the great the Mother of Harlots, &amp;c. rules and reigns not only at <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy, Spain</hi> and other popiſh Countryes where the Romiſh Sect prevails, as ſome private <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſts</hi> have imagined; but is univerſally to be found, reigning thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughout all the Sects in <hi>Christendom,</hi> and in the whole World.</note> the great red Dragon that gets into Heaven, and the Beaſt that ariſeth out of the Sea or Waters, on which the Whore ſiſteth, and the falſe Prophet, and the three unclean Spirits like Frogs, that come out of their Mouths, that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth the Earth, and fills
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36997:19"/>it with Violence; it is this Woman, this Myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> the great, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Earth, that is drunk with the Blood of the Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus; and by her Sorceries are all Nations deceived, and in her was (and is) found the Blood of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and of Saints, and of all that were (and are) ſlain upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>Now the Voice from Heaven is heard, which ſaith, <hi>Come out of her my People, that ye partake not of her Sins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues:</hi> And all that hear obey and follow this heavenly Voice, come to be led out of Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> into the heavenly City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which comes down from God out of Heaven, and to be made Citizens there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who are at Unity within themſelves; and though the Gates ſtand open there ſhall in no wiſe enter any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abomination, or maketh a Lye; but they which are written in the Lamb's Book of Life: Here all is ſhut out that entered in through Sin and Tranſgreſſion, and through the Subtilty and Lyes of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and a Redemption and Reſtoration into the glorious primitive Eſtate, that God made
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36997:19"/>Mankind in in the Beginning, where his Mind Heart and Conſcience is ſet at Liberty, cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and purified from all that did defile them, and here he is delivered from following all his carnal Inventions,
<note place="margin">☞</note> private Opinions and Notions, where the Envy, Anger and Wrath is exerciſed, into the peaceable uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Light, and Love to the whole Creation of God.</p>
            <p>But while People are carnaly-minded, and their Conſciences darkened &amp; defiled they are captivated by a private ſelfiſh Spirit, and are bound under ſome dark affected Opinion or other about Religion; in this State ſome will be for <hi>Paul.</hi> ſome for <hi>Apello,</hi> ſome for <hi>Cophas;</hi> but none for Chriſt; ſome of one Sect or Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and of one Sort &amp; Form of Worſhip, and ſome of another; but all bound under one Link or other of the Chain of Darkneſs, and are Slaves to the Prince thereof, who hath got the Rule in their Minds, Hearts and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſuch of his Vaſſals, as are inclined to ſeem religious, he will furniſh them with a Form, Likeneſs and Patern, if need be, even of Heavenly Things themſelves, according to the State, Place and Country they inhabit, and the Region of Darkneſs and Shadow of Death they dwell under; whether in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> or in any other Part of the World; hence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36997:20"/>many are bound in their Conſciences, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip according to the Precepts and Commands of <hi>Mahomet</hi> or the Turkiſh <hi>Alcoron,</hi> others according to the Traditions of the ſcattered <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Indians;</hi> others according to the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Maſs Book,</hi> and other Invented Trumpery, others according to the divers Sorts of invented <hi>Liturgies</hi> and Forms of Worſhip, Likeneſſes and Images, which they have ſet up in their carnal Minds, and darkened Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings wherein their corrupt Faiths, and defiled Conſciences, are imployed as Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions to contend for, and vindicate every one his own private carnal Opinion, Tradition and Form of Worſhip: And the ſame Spirit of Darkneſs, that leads into theſe Diverſities of Opinions, &amp; humane, carnal Inventions about the Worſhip of God;
<note place="margin">The Fruit of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hating the Light and running, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and working in Darkneſs.</note> leads Men to hate, * envy and perſecute one another about them.</p>
            <p>And all theſe Things come to paſs amongſt Mankind, for want of believing in the Light, Grace, Spirit and Power of God, that ſhines, appears and operates in the Mind. Heart and Conſcience of Mankind, according to the State it finds him in, either to reprove or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, juſtifie or condemn, which Light,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36997:20"/>Grace and Spirit is one, and leads all that obey it and follow it into Oneneſs of Mind, &amp; One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, and into the One ſtanding and everlaſting Worſhip, which is in the Spirit and in the Truth, where Acceptance is felt, and the Light of God's Countenance enjoyed, the Partition-Wall broken down, and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſlain, and the Serpent's Head bruiſed within, by the ſpringing up of the promiſed Seed, and powerful Appearance of Chriſt within, who leadeth into that bleſſed Love and Charity, which never faileth, which thinketh no Evil, where the rejoycing is not in Iniquity, but in the Truth.</p>
            <p>And whoever thou art that readeſt theſe Things, and art not come to witneſs within thy ſelf, the virtuous Efficacy of the Power, Life and Blood of Jeſus, to cleanſe, purge and purifie thy Mind, Heart and Conſcience, from all that doth defile, and ſet them at per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Liberty to ſerve the Lord, and to lead thee into the heavenly City, where the Book of Life is kept, and to ſee thy Name written therein, and alſo his Name imprinted in thy Forehead, bearing his heavenly Image as thou haſt born the earthly; I ſay, except thou knoweſt theſe Things wrought by the Spirit and Power of God in thee and for thee; thy Mind, Heart and Conſcience remains defil'd,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36997:21"/>and under Bondage to thine own Inventions, private Opinions and Notions; and he that is called the Prince of the Air, rules in thy heart, and thou art captivated, and carried away with the windy Doctrines, Rudimens and carnal Ordinances, and Traditions of men, and art taſting, touching and handling thoſe Things, which periſh with the uſing; and art prone &amp; liable to bite, tear, murder and devour thy Brother and Neighbour about them; ſo art as a whited Wall, and painted Sepulchre, and profeſſing Hypocrite, and Titular Chriſtian, a direct Phanatick and Sectarian, and art like <hi>Cain</hi> a Fugitive in the Earth, which God hath curſed, that brings forth Bryars and Thorns, which tear the Sheep, and hurt the Lilly; this is thy State and Condition, let thy Talk, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Notion, Opinion, Form and Faſhion of Religion be what it will, and whether thou art a <hi>Jew, Mahometan, Papiſt,</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> while thy Mind, Heart and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is defiled, darkened, captivated and bound under with the Chains of Opinion, Tradition and Precepts of men thou canſt not enjoy Liberty of Conſcience thy ſelf, nor ſuffer others; and if thou compaſſeſt Sea and Land to make Proſelytes to thy Opinion and Tradition, and haſt Power to force and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel an Outward Conformity to the ſame, thou
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36997:21"/>makeſt them two fold more the Children of Hell then before. Force, Cruelty and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence may make <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Formaliſts,</hi> but <hi>No True Worſhippers of God in the Spirit,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtians indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, to Force and Compel by Corporal Puniſhments in Matters of Conſcience and Religion, is infallibly contrary to, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with, the very Nature of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Being of <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> And among whomſoever its found and practiſed, 'tis an evident Demonſtration that the Pure Religion they are ignorant of, and Strangers to; and ſuch are only <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Opinion,</hi> and of a dark, narrow, private, ſelf-conceited ſpirit, priding it ſelf with it own Notions and lofty Imaginations, grounded upon the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Tradition received from his Fore-Fathers, and the <hi>carnal Comprehenſions and Conceivings of his own corrupt Heart from the ancient Writings of Holy Men:</hi> hence it is that every Sect and Opinioniſt, like ſo many Beaſts with Horns, puſh one againſt another, hate, bite, tear and devour one another, each endeavouring to ſit down as a Queen in the Seat of the Scornful (exerciſing themſelves in things that are too high) Imperiouſly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, trying and judging his Brother and Neighbour, who differs from him by his ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36997:22"/>carnal, dark, exalted ſpirit, who paſſeth under and aſſumes the Name of a <hi>Sheep,</hi> though in Nature and Work he be a <hi>Wolf;</hi> and if this Beaſt of Prey hath Horns and Claws ſtrong enough to make Spoil according to its Nature, it would hardly leave the Bones till the morrow: This is the <hi>Generation whoſe Teeth are as Swords,
<note place="margin">Proverbs 30 14.</note> and their Jaw-Teeth as Knives to devour the Poor from off the Earth, and the Needy from among men;</hi> this is the <hi>Generation</hi> alſo <hi>who are pure in their own Eyes, yet are not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from their Filthineſs;</hi> but is as a polluted Leper, full of Sores from the Crown of the Head to the Sole of the Foot: From this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration ariſeth the Cry and Violence againſt the Innocent, as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> haling them before Magiſtrates, and hurrying them to Goals, Inquiſitions, Gallowſes and Fire, tearing the Fleſh from the Bones, and the Liſe from the Body about Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Church, Faith, Worſhip and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, all which is infallibly the Fruit and Effect of that Spirit of <hi>Cain,</hi> that Envious Sacrifices, that can Worſhip with one Hand, and Murder with the other; call God <hi>Father,</hi> and with the ſame Tongue call Chriſt Jeſus a <hi>Blaſphemer, Deceiver</hi> and <hi>Child of the Devil,</hi> and lay their Wicked Hands upon him, as an
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36997:22"/>
               <hi>Evil-doer</hi> not fit to live: this is and hath been the Work of all the Private, Carnal, Dark, Self-conceited Opinionſts in <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> who are all Members of the Falſe Church, and of the Great City <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> whoſe Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens are all of <hi>defiled Minds, corrupt Heares,</hi> and <hi>darkened, miſguided, if not ſeared Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences:</hi> And none of this Work hath been, nor never will be found in the true Church, nor among the Citizens of the heavenly <hi>Feruſalem,</hi> whoſe Defence and Weapons never was nor will be Carnal, but Spiritual, and Mighty through God, to the breaking and caſting down every thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the Proſperity thereof; whoſe Warfare was never againſt mens Bodies, Lives nor Eſtates, to deſtroy the One, and poſſeſs the Other; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do the Thoughts thereof enter into the Heart of a True <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to Hurt his Brother or Neighbour, becauſe of Difference in Religion, and Underſtanding of things relating thereto: Yet the True Church hath its Way and Means of Defence, and every living Member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is in its Place and Capacity, engaged and bound by the Law of the Spirit of Life and in the Univerſal Love of God,
<note place="margin">☞</note> to be watchful and diligent againſt the creeping in of Selfiſh Private Opinions, and the broaching of Damnable Doctrines, or the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36997:23"/>growing up of any hurtful Weeds in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God; but as I have ſaid, this Defence is <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> viz. <hi>the Light, Power and Spirit of God revealed in the Inward Parts; this Church puts on the whole Armour of Light, the Sword of the Spirit, the Helmet of Salvation, the Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſs, and the very Feet ſhod with the Preparation of the Goſpel</hi> (or with that which prepares the Way of the Goſpel); I ſay, theſe are Weapons of the True Church, and of every Member thereof, whereby thoſe that ſay they are <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>are not,</hi> are tryed, and found Lyars, and the Errors and Doctrines of <hi>Balaam detected,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read <hi>Rev.</hi> 1, 2, 3. and the Lord open thy Underſtanding.</note> and the Teachings of the <hi>Woman Jezabel,</hi> who calleth her ſelf a Propheteſs, <hi>reſiſted;</hi> yea, all the Faults and Errors of the <hi>Seven Churches</hi> are reproved and judged by the Son of God, <hi>who holdeth the Seven Stars in his Right Hand,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                  </label> and walks in the midſt of the
<note n="‖" place="margin">The Son of God is in the midſt of his People, who are like Gold tryed in the Fire, and made Veſſels of Honour, to hold the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Treafure, and Temples of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God; this is the true Church, that what ſhe bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and looſeth on Earth, is confirmed in Heaven, againſt which the Gates of Hell cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail; out of the Pale of this Church there's no Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: This is the Holy Church that cannot err, where the infallible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, even in whom the Son of God lives and walks in the midſt, and hath by his bright and powerful Appearance broken down and removed all that is contrary to him, and ſet the Mind, Heart and Conſcience at perfect Liberty from all Private Opinions, Selfiſh Conceivings, Dark Thoughts and Lofty Imaginations, which once did defile them: In this Church is the one Mind, one Heart and one Judgment; and ſhe hath the one Faith, one Baptiſm and one Lord, &amp; is as a Coat woven from top to bottom, without Seam: And all the Members of this Church are livin Stones, fitted and ſquared for the Houſe and Habitation of God; in the fitting and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of which, the Sound or Noiſe of the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Tool is not heard, nor Self had in any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; but the Praiſe and Glory of all is to God, the Worker of all in his People; to whom all Honour is due forever and evermore.</note> Seven Golden Candleſticks;</hi> and thoſe that turn not at his Reproof, Repent, and are Reformed by his Judgments, will aſſuredly in the End hear this fatal
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36997:23"/>Sentence, <hi>I gave her ſpace to repent, and ſhe repented not; behold I will caſt her into a Bed, and them that commit Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with her, into great Tribulation; I will kill her Children with Death, and all the Churches ſhall know, that I am he that ſearcheth the Reins and Hearts, &amp; giveth to every one according to his Works;</hi> He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:36997:24"/>
            <head>Something after, which ſhould have been placed before.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REader,</hi> I would have thee ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh &amp; conſider what thou readeſt in this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and with the Meaſure of Divine Light, which ſhines in thy Mind, Heart and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (whether thou be Darkneſs or Light, a Believer or an Infidel) take a perfect View of thy ſelf, and thou mayeſt by the Light thereof infallibly perceive and know, Whether thou art
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36997:24"/>a Member of the
<note n="*" place="margin">None can be of the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they walk in the Light, learn of the Grace, and profit by the Manifeſtation of the Spirit of God, given to them, and is preſent with them, convincing, reproving &amp; judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all and every Appearance of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and ready to teach &amp; lead into all Good; and it is thoſe only that are led and guided by the <hi>ſpirit of God</hi> that are his Sons &amp; Daughters, and Members of the holy <hi>church,</hi> which is in God; he that can receive it, let him.</note> Holy Catholick Church, or whether thou art of ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Opinion or Sect, which only calls it ſelf ſo; and whether thy Mind, Heart and Conſcience-are clenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſet at Liberty from all that did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file and imbondage them; or, whether thou art corrupted &amp; defiled, captivated and bound under with the Chains of Darkneſs, Superſtitious Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Corrupt Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Selfiſh Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, kindling thy Sacrifices with Coals from thy own Altar, and walking in the Light of thy own Sparks, by the <hi>Eye</hi> or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36997:25"/>Light of God, which runs to and fro through the Earth, and ſearcheth thy Heart, tryeth thy Reins and ſheweth unto thee thy Thoughts, thou mayeſt ſee thy own <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition, how thou ſtandeſt in the Sight of the Lord:</hi> &amp; if thy <hi>Mind be ſpiritual, thou</hi> haſt <hi>Life &amp; Peace; if thy Heart be pure, thou</hi> ſeeſt <hi>the Lord; if thy Conſcience be purged from dead Works, thou</hi> art <hi>a Servant of the living God, and findeſt Acceptance with him, being alive to Righteouſneſs, and dead to Sin:</hi> but <hi>if thou doſt Evil, Sin lies at thy Door, and he that ſaves his People from their Sins thou art ignorant of, and Death, the Wages thereof, attends thee,</hi> profeſs what thou wilt, and let thy <hi>notion</hi> &amp; <hi>opinion</hi> be what it will, let thy <hi>form</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> be what it will, whether thou art a <hi>Jew, Mahumetan, Papiſt</hi> or <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> this is the Word of Truth to thee, whether thou wilt hear or forbear, thou ſhalt find it ſealed upon thee in the Day of the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36997:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
